Fahad Akhtar

+61 04260 41088 | fahad.khn72@gmail.com | Melbourne | https://www.linkedin.com/in/fahadakhtar28/

Education

La Trobe University

MS in Data Science

Nov 2022 - Oct 2024

Melbourne, Australia

AKGEC Ghaziabad, India

B.Tech in Mechanical Engineering

Aug 2017 - Aug 2021

Technical Skills

Languages / Tools: Python, MySQL, R, SAS enterprise miner, Informatica power Centre, Excel

Data Visualization: Tableau, PowerBI, SAS viya

Libraries: Pandas, Tensorflow, Numpy, Matplotlib, spacy, Scikitlearn

Statistical Analysis: Hypothesis Testing, A/B testing, Statistical techniques, Meta-analysis

Skills: Data Science, Data analysis & reporting, deep Learning, ETL, NLP, JIRA, problem solving, project management,

AWS

Summary

Data scientist with an experience in raw data ingestion through REST API, cleaning the data using python and using it to draw insights using techniques like machine learning & deep learning. I have also leveraged platforms like PowerBI & SAS viya to draw insights through data visualization and reporting. I have previously worked on ETL projects during my tenure at Cognizant.

Experience

Data Analyst Intern

Cisco innovation central

July 2024 – Nov 2024 Melbourne, AUS

- Ingested JSON data via REST API and utilized Python for data cleaning hence improving the process speed by 20%.
- Enabled dashboard creation to visualize space utilization data from IoT sensors at La Trobe University assisting in efficient space utilization of the available spaces.
- Coordinated with stakeholders to keep them updated with data driven insights and proposed improvement avenues.

Programmer Analyst (AIA)

Cognizant tech. sol.

Aug 2021 – Nov 2022

Pune, IND

- Enhanced data accuracy by 15% for BI teams using Informatica by implementing data cleaning, regex and validation rules.
- Used address doctor with Informatica data quality to validate customer data for a U.S gas provider.
- Collaborated with teams to create efficient data workflows, improving data processing speed by 20%.

Projects

- Sentiment Analysis: Conducted sentiment analysis on Amazon customer reviews by applying NLP techniques, categorizing customer sentiments to inform strategic improvements in sales and enhance customer satisfaction.
- Customer Churn Analysis: Employed neural networks to analyze telecom customer churn, optimizing hyper
 parameters to achieve strong predictive accuracy, enabling targeted retention strategies based on
 comprehensive performance metrics.

- **Credit Risk Analysis**: Implemented **random forest classification** on the German credit dataset to assess customer credit risk, using cost matrices to improve customer benchmarking to avoid fraud.
- **Customer Segmentation**: Utilized **K-means clustering** on a car insurance dataset to create customer segments based on age, employment, and demographic data, offering recommendations for targeted marketing and service personalization.

References

Available upon request